# 这全是老活啊
This is a traditional dish.
# 老宴会菜
A traditional banquet dish.
# 这真漂亮啊大爷
This is so beautiful, Da Ye.
# 漂亮吧
Beautiful, isn’t it.
# 这是一个国宴大菜
This is a big state banquet dish.
# 二伯好
Hi Er Bai
# 大爷好
Hi Da Ye
# 刚强好
Hi Gang Qiang
# 师父好
Hi master
# 今天给了我一个很艰巨的任务
I have been given a difficult task today.
# 我们导演说了
Our director
# 要让做一个50块钱以下的
asked me to make a dish under 50 yuan.
# 国宴菜
A state banquet dish.
# 咱们今天做一什么呢
The dish we are going to make today is
# 香菇瓤菜心
Shiitake mushrooms and stuffed choy sum.
# 这是一个国宴的大菜
This is a big state banquet dish.
# 它有素菜
It has vegetables.
# 但是还有点荤是吧
And also, some meat.
# 我第一步先把香菇处理一下
I’m going to prepare the shiitake mushrooms first.
# 点个火
Light up the stove.
# 我的节奏就比较快
My pace is pretty fast.
# 你们得跟上一点
You need to keep up.
# 还有两节葱
Two short pieces of spring onions.
# 来两片姜
Two pieces of ginger.
# 来点油
Some oil.
# 看出来您要做个大菜啊
Looks like you are going to make a big dish.
# 咱把葱姜煸煸
Let’s stir-fry the spring onions and the ginger.
# 这是一个花菇
This is a flower mushroom (a type of shiitake mushroom).
# 什么叫花菇
What is a flower mushroom?
# 看看吧
Look,
# 这菇在花菇里边是属于上品
This is a high quality one.
# 这样的花菇
This type of flower mushroom is
# 肉厚
thick
# 泡的时候也要讲究一点
Pay attention when soaking them.
# 第一遍先洗 洗完了以后
Wash them first, after the washing
# 泡点凉水回软
soak them in cold water until they are soft.
# 然后要把香菇汤要留下来
And then keep the soaking liquid.
# 然后把香菇都处理干净了
Then clean the mushrooms.
# 我们用葱姜
We are going to stir-fry them with
# 煸炒
the spring onions and ginger.
# 还有耗油 耗油香菇啊
Also oyster sauce, oyster sauce shiitake mushrooms.
# 再来一点水
And some more water.
# 一搁耗油和香菇烧的很香的
The mushrooms smell very nice once the oyster sauce is added.
# 对
Yes.
# 搁上水
Add water.
# 最后呢还要搁一点老抽
Add some dark soy sauce at last.
# 搁点糖
Some sugar.
# 这耗油香菇必须搁糖
Oyster mushrooms must have sugar in it.
# 对 提鲜
Yes. It adds a savory note.
# 糖
Sugar
# 盐要少搁啊
Don’t add too much salt.
# 白胡椒啊
White pepper.
# 最关键的啊
And most importantly,
# 黄酒
huangjiu rice wine.
# 倍儿香
Smells amazing.
# 这香菇 煨一煨
Simmer the mushroom for a little while.
# 如果着急的话
If in a hurry,
# 我们就改蒸了
we could steam it instead.
# 不着急咱就可以直接煮
If not in a hurry, we could just boil it.
# 这香菇就OK了
Mushrooms are ready.
# 这时候啊我们焯水 菜心要焯水
Now we blanch the choy sum.
# 在这儿之前
Before that,
# 我们还要备了一点金华火腿
We need to prepare some Jinghua ham.
# 时间问题
Due to the time,
# 我们先蒸上
We are going to steam it first.
# 大约要一小时
For about an hour.
# 葱姜黄酒三样东西
Three things, spring onions, ginger and huangjiu rice wine.
# 开始蒸香菇
Let’s steam the mushrooms.
# 这个时候我们等着锅开
While we are waiting for the water to boil,
# 我这边先处理这虾
I’m going to prepare the shrimps.
# 瓤馅的可以用鸡馅鱼馅还有虾馅
Apart from shrimp mince, the stuffing could also be chicken mince or fish mince.
# 这虾已经洗干净了
The shrimps have already been cleaned.
# 是吧
Yes.
# 我们干毛巾把水分沾干
We are using a dry towel to soak up the water.
# 挑完虾线的
The veins have already been removed.
# 对
Yes.
# 咱山东菜叫虾腻子
Minced shrimp are called Xia Ni Zi in Shandong cuisine.
# 广东菜虾胶
or Xia Jiao in Guangdon cuisine.
# 对 这个弄干了以后
Yes. Shrimps are dried.
# 很快啊 嗯
Very fast.
# 你看
Look
# 百花的已经是虾胶了
Xia jiao is called ‘hundred flowers (minced shrimps)’.
# 这个虾处理的时候特别快
It can be made very quickly.
# 一拍
Give it a pat.
# 再一剁 好了
And then chop, done.
# 粤菜的百花馅可以粗一点
Minced shrimps used in Guangdong cuisine doesn’t need to be very fine.
# 淮扬菜我们要细一点
It needs to finer in Huaiyang cuisine.
# 有时候我们这刀背要厚的话
If the spine of our knife is thick
# 我们又翻过来 捶
We turn the knife around, hammer it.
# 这叫捶虾胶
This is called hammering the minced shrimp.
# 武刀的刀背就要厚
Chopping knife’s spine is thick.
# 你还得打点肥膘增加虾的香气
You also need to add some pork fat to boost the aroma of the shrimps.
# 虾胶好了
The minced shrimp is ready.
# 好.
Right.
# 这个肥膘呢用硬肥膘
For the pork fat, use hard fat only.
# 像上面这层蔫皮啊
The skin on the top,
# 就不要了这上面有筋
needs to be trimmed off because it has tendons in it.
# 好水开了 这个焯水不能搁油
The water is boiling now. Do not add oil to the water while blanching.
# 搁油因为你瓤馅的时候瓤不上去了
it will be hard to stuff the vegetables if oil is added.
# 所以就是给它焯软
So just blanch it until soft.
# 这个菜心呢我们要买叫矮脚黄
The choy sum we are using today is called Ai Jiao Huang.
# 短粗头大
Short and thick with a big stalk.
# 肉厚 它面乎
It is thick and tender.
# 把菜心一开二
Cut the choy sum open into two pieces.
# 帮我冲一冲啊
Give it a rinse.
# 冲凉
Rinse until it cools.
# 因为现在这虾呀
The shrimps nowadays
# 都是养殖虾
are usually farmed.
# 它这胶性蛋白质不太丰富
They have less protein in them.
# 肥膘肉要多给一点
More pork fat is needed.
# 刀背砸
Hammer with the back of the knife.
# 广东的牛肉丸不是用大棒子敲么
When making beef balls in Guangdong cuisine, they are usually beaten with a big stick.
# 拿刀剁呢是把肥膘里的筋斩断
Chopping it with the knife cuts up the tendons in the fat.
# 齐活 这个环节好了
Done, this step is completed.
# 黄酒
Huangjiu rice wine.
# 葱姜酒水
Spring onions, ginger and huangjiu rice wine.
# 胡椒粉
Whit pepper powder.
# 搁点胡椒粉
Add some white pepper.
# 给来一点鸡蛋啊
And some egg.
# 盐 盐没少搁啊
Salt. Plenty of salt.
# 葱姜酒水 蛋清
Spring onions, ginger and huangjiu rice wine, egg white.
# 半个蛋清
Half egg white.
# 淀粉玉米淀粉
Starch, corn starch.
# 顺时针
Clock-wise.
# 为什么呢 现在虾胶啊
A lot of minced shrimps
# 它有时候打出来以后它不脆
are not crunchy sometimes.
# 我们搁点蛋清增加它蛋白质的凝固
We add some egg white to help the protein to stick better.
# 好了
Okay.
# 打成上劲儿
Beat and mix it until fully combined.
# 国宴菜 标准
State banquet dish, standard.
# 菜心也要吸干水分
We need to drain the choy sum as well.
# 是吧
Right.
# 尤其菜心的头这部分
Especially the water in the stalks.
# 要把它吸干水分
Remove all the water.
# 不吸干它不好沾啊
wet stalks are harder to combine (with the stuffing).
# 稀汤挂水的
Too watery
# 搁淀粉馅上去
Sprinkle some starch powder,
# 它不会掉下来
so it won’t fall off.
# 这事就快差不离了
Almost there.
# 差不离咯
# 这是这全是老活
These are the traditions.
# 老宴会菜
An old dish from the state banquet.
# 香菇咕咚咕咚也差不多了
The shiitake mushrooms are almost done.
# 该剂虾胶了吧大爷
Let’s squeeze the minced shrimps, Da Ye.
# 一个
One.
# 两个
Two.
# 挤这丸子呢手就有准了
So much skills in the hands while squeezing the shrimp balls.
# 大小都一样
Same sizes.
# 这是几十年的工作经验
This is many years of experience.
# 看着啊
Look.
# 拿一小板 抹点油
Put some oil on.
# 其实在家里头用勺也可以
You can also use a spoon at home.
# 如果说没有小竹坯子的话
If you don’t have this little baboon tool.
# 对
Yes.
# 要光滑饱满
Smooth and chubby.
# 要鱼肉更白
It would be whiter if you are using fish.
# 鱼肉鸡腻子
A mixture of fish and chick mince
# 而且还更细腻
makes it finer.
# 但是鱼丸子有一个问题
But there is one problem with fish balls.
# 蒸的时候火不能太旺了
Don’t put the flame too hot when steaming them.
# 这鱼丸子一蒸跟马蜂窝似的
There will be a lot of holes on the fish balls.
# 这真漂亮大爷
This is so beautiful, Da Ye.
# 漂亮吧
Beautiful, right?
# 待会你看
You will see,
# 再点上火腿末更漂亮
It is even prettier after the ham is added.
# 为什么要点点火腿末
Why do we need to add some ham?
# 因为这菜很清淡
Because this dish is quite light.
# 当你吃着一点火腿末的时候
When you taste the ham mince,
# 又火腿的那种咸香
The ham gives a savory note.
# 对有鲜味 有香味
True, taste savory, and smells good.
# 火腿呢
For the ham,
# 搁点黄酒搁点葱姜给蒸一下
steam it with some huangjiu rice wine, spring onions and ginger.
# 蒸完了怎么保存呢
How do we keep it after it’s steamed?
# 把它肥的去掉
Trim off the fat.
# 找一个小罐
Find a little jar.
# 放点咱们植物油给它封上
Seal it with some vegetable oil.
# 什么时候用把油一冲接着用
Rinse off the oil before you use it.
# 但火腿买来一定要是蒸熟
Ham must be fully steamed after purchased.
# 火腿末
Minced ham.
# 火腿有几个部位啊
What are the different parts for hams?
# 最好的是上腰峰
Upper loan is the best.
# 那块肉特别红
It is a very red piece.
# 真正好火腿那都是好几年啊
The real good ham is usually ripened for years.
# 画龙点睛
Make the finishing point.
# 这就好看了
Making it looking good.
# 这蒸的时间很短
The steam time is short.
# 三 分钟开锅三分钟
3 minutes after the water boils.
# 找着教材书上的感觉了
A textbook dish.
# 应该说就我知道的
From what I know,
# 有50年
It has been 50 years,
# 就说我50年前
50 years ago,
# 就我来到饭店
When I started to work at (Beijing) Hotel.
# 就有这道菜
This dish has already existed.
# 锅开了
The water is boiling.
# 您慢点大爷 锅边儿烫
Slowly Da Ye. The pot is burning.
# 这边蒸着 这边把冬菇
While this is steaming, let’s
# 也勾出来
make a slurry for the mushrooms.
# 葱姜挑出去 吃其味不见其物
Take out the spring onions and ginger. We only need their flavour.
# 淀粉勾芡
Make a slurry with corn starch.
# 水淀粉
Here’s the slurry.
# 好了
Done.
# 菜就熟了
It is now cooked.
# 行了
Fine.
# 明油亮芡儿
Some finishing oil to brighten the slurry.
# 你看我这好了啊
Look, I’m finishing the dish here.
# 嘿 一蒸倍儿漂亮啊大爷
Hey, so pretty once it is steamed, Da Ye.
# 还一白汁呢
There’s also a white source
# 对
Yes.
# 什么细节都不能少
We can’t miss any detail.
# 白汁呢是用好鸡汤清鸡汤
Using good chicken stock, clear chicken stock, to make the white sauce.
# 盐 搁点糖
Salt, add some sugar.
# 胡椒粉
White pepper powder.
# 先调一汁
Mix first.
# 米汤芡儿
Looks like rice soup.
# 玻璃芡儿
Clear slurry.
# 好了
Done.
# 要是有鸡油来点鸡油
Add some chicken oil if you have any.
# 鸡油亮啊
Chicken oil makes it shiny.
# 对
Yes.
# 出锅了
Out of the pot.
# 走着
Let’s go.
# 出水见芙蓉
Like lotus flowers just out of water.
# 浇白汁啊
Pour the white sauce over.
# 浇完这汁呢这虾才能亮
The shrimps are sparkling after the sauce is poured over.
# 老菜还是鲜啊
Traditional dish is delicious.
# 菜心呢也给点儿味儿
The choy sum adds flavours as well.
# 该香菇了
Mushrooms.
# 筷子
Chopsticks.
# 知我者二伯也
Er Bai knows me the best.
# 这个帽儿一定要朝上 得了
The caps must face up. Done.
# 菌中鲜海中鲜
The umami of the mushrooms and the umami of the seafood.
# 这地道啊
Authentic.
# 二伯您尝尝
Er Bai, please have a try.
# 给我
Give it to me.
# 先吃虾
Shrimps first.
# 哎
oh
# 这虾Q弹
The shrimp is bouncy.
# 鲜香无比
Incomparably delicious.
# 是不是
Isn’t it?
# 颜色漂亮
Beautiful colour.
# 这虾胶打的好
The minced shrimps are very well made.
# 油菜碧绿
The choy sum is green.
# 清鲜爽口
Crisp and refreshing.
# 这香菇蒸的真是入味儿
The flavour penetrated the mushrooms very well.
# 菌香味儿非常足
The flavour of the mushroom itself is very strong.
# 层次感
Goo layering of flavours.
# 能吃出三种不同的味道
You can taste three different flavours.
# 虾胶的味儿
Flavour of the minced shrimps.
# 油菜的清香可口
Fresh taste of the choy sum.
# 香菇这菌香味
Aroma from the mushrooms.
# 倍儿浓郁
Very rich taste.
# 三种食材
Three ingredients
# 合为一体
fused into one dish.
# 融合的好
Good fusion.
# 这就是什么
Guess what
# 大爷
Da Ye
# 还原
re-creating
# 50年前的北京饭店的国宴菜
a state banquet dish made in Beijing Hotel 50 years ago
# 怕我们忘了本不忘初心
is a reminder for us to remain true to our original aspiration.
# 最后有一句话向大爷学习
We need to learn from Da Ye.
# 向大爷致敬
Paying my respect to Da Ye.
# 谢谢二伯
Thank you Er Bai.
# 大爷
Da Ye.
# 一菜
One dish,
# 三种吃法
three ways to eat.
# 菌类的菌中鲜
The umami of the mushrooms.
# 虾有海中鲜
The umami of the shrimps.
# 还有油菜的爽脆
And the crispy vegetables.
# 又学一招大爷
I’m learning new skills from Da Ye again.
# 大美中国菜 大国工匠
Great Chinese cuisine, great chef.
# 给大爷点赞
Give Da Ye a thumb-up.
# 谢谢刚强
Thank you Gang Qiang.
# 我发现你现在
I found that
# 比我还会夸人啊
now you are better at praising people then me.
# 好
Good.
# 大多数菜肴都需要过油
Oil is needed a lot in many dishes.
# 家庭日常的烹饪
In everyday cooking,
# 还是很心疼油的
it feels bad to use too much oil,
# 然后就想问一下
So, the question is
# 平时油循环使用几次比较适宜
how many times can we reuse cooking oil
# 在家里边
at home?
# 因为大爷在家里
I often cook
# 也经常做饭
at home.
# 也会
And usually
# 碰到这种同样的问题
I would encounter the same problem.
# 比如说
For instance,
# 我们今天要炸鱼
we need to try fish today.
# 炸完这鱼的一个油
After the oil is used,
# 让它控一控
let it sit for a while.
# 沉淀一下
to sediment.
# 然后弄个油篦子
Then, use a oil strainer
# 倒到一个小的小碗里头
pour the oil into a small bowl.
# 就搁起来了
keep it there.
# 这个等下次再炸鱼的时候
When you need to fry fish again later,
# 再添点油
add some fresh oil to it,
# 再继续炸.
then use it again.
# 这儿能炸五六次就可以了
In this way, the oil can be reused for five to six times.
# 五六次没问题哈
Five to six times without any problems.
# 这个油是专门炸鱼的油
This oil is used for frying fish only.
# 它也不会不健康了
Is this unhealthy?
# 没有
No,
# 这个油只要不变色
as long as the colour of the oil doesn’t change.
# 比如说我一下油
For example, say I’m reusing the oil,
# 这鱼一下锅一炸
If the fish turns black
# 这鱼就黑了
while frying,
# 这说明这油就不行了
this means the oil cannot be used anymore.
# 只要它不变色
As long as the colour doesn’t change,
# 我们再添点新油
We can add some fresh oil to it,
# 就一点问题没有
This would have no problem at all.
# 但是比如我们要炸个素丸子
But, if we want to fry vegetarian meatballs,
# 炸个油饼
Or a youbing (deep-fried cake,
# 是吧
right,
# 炸的油
the oil needed for that
# 这油就比较多
is quite a lot.
# 这油多了怎么办呢
So what can we do if there’s a lot of oil？
# 因为它炸的全是素的
Because everything that has been fried in these oil are vegetarian,
# 我们在炒菜当中
(the oil can be reused) when we are making stir-fried dishe.
# 炒一些肉菜
Like stir frying a meat dish,
# 或者烧个鱼或者做什么
or cooking a fish
# 我们添加点油
We could reuse some that oil.
# 因为它是炸过菜的油
Because the oil has been used to fry vegetables,
# 它香
it is very aromatic.
# 逐渐的带着就用进去了
We can use it as we cook.
# 另外我们还可以
We could also use,
# 比如有那种
For example,
# 棉纸
paper towers
# 是吧
right,
# 给它过滤一下
to have the oil filtered.
# 它的颜色也会会好一点
The colour of the oil will be better.
# 这个
In this way,
# 也是用五六次就可以了
the oil could also be used for five to six times.